>> Jem Young: 我们来谈谈 VIM。
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: Let's talk about VIM.
>> Jem Young: VIM 代表 Vi 改进，
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: VIM stands for Vi Improved,
它是一个类似于 PHP的元定义类。
it's one of those meta-definitions
kind of like PHP.
>> Jem Young: PHP 代表什么 ?
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: What does PHP stand for,
anybody?
> > Jem Young: 就像这些书呆子中的一个。
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: It's like
one of these nerd jerks.
PHP 代表 PHP 超文本预处理器，
PHP stands for PHP Hypertext Preprocessor,
这是一个自我参考的定义，就像 Vi 改进了， VIM。
it's a self-referential definition,
just like Vi Improved, VIM.
但它是什么，是文本编辑器吗 ?
But what it is, it's text editor?
VI 很强大，因为它几乎在每一个服务器上。
VI is powerful because it's
on almost every server.
因此，如果要编辑文件，那么必须以某种方式执行该操作。
So if you wanna edit a file,
you have to do that somehow.
这些都是我起步时理所当然的事情。
Again, these are things that when I
was starting off I took for granted.
当然可以在我的 VS 码，或网络风暴中打开
Of course, I can just open it in my
VS Code or sublime or a web storm or
任何 IT 正在使用的信息。
whatever IT are using.
服务器将具有其中任何一个，您可能可以进行安装，但是
Servers will have any of that,
you can probably install it but
如果你有 1000 台服务器可能是个麻烦
if you have 1,000 servers,
it's probably be a hassle.
VI 将会在您拥有的每台服务器上，因此要编辑是一件好事
VI is gonna be on every server you have,
so it's a good thing to use to edit
主要使用工程师的档案
files which primarily it's
always use it engineers,
我们只编辑文件，创建新的文件，然后进行编辑。
we just edit files, we create new
files we edit them then we run them.
>> Jem Young: 那么，从 VI 开始，实际上是执行我们的 VI
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: So, to start VI,
well, actually enforce our VI you
应该知道这两种模式，这在第一次是很吓人的。
should know about the modes and this
seems really intimidating at first but
当我们开始使用它时就会有道理
it will make sense when we start using it.
它具有插入方式，用于编辑文本。
It has insert mode and
that's for editing text.
它具有命令方式。
It has command mode.
这样做的原因是复制，粘贴，查找，之类的。
That's for doing things like copy,
paste, find, things like that.
它具有搜索，保存，退出之类的最后一行方式。
It has last line mode for searching,
saving, exiting, other things like that.
有三种模式，似乎是很混淆的。
It seems really confusing
that there is three modes.
但是，当你想到一个 GUI 所做的工作时，它实际上也有多种模式。
But, when you think about what a GUI does,
it actually has multiple modes as well.
你只是不注意它只在一个接口里
You just don't notice it cuz it's
all in one single interface.
我最伟大的是你不能用鼠标
The great thing about VI
is you can't use a mouse.
它迫使您不要使用鼠标。
It forces you to not use a mouse.
我的意思是，我肯定有一些插件让你用鼠标。
I mean, I'm sure there's plugins
that let you use a mouse.
但是如果你真的很擅长六
But, if you're really good at VI,
你会比有鼠标和键盘的人更快
you're gonna be much faster than
someone with a mouse and keyboard.
因为一只老鼠，你不考虑它，但是你打字，
Because a mouse, you don't think
about it but you're typing,
然后你想做点什么移动你的鼠标
and then you wanna do something,
you move your mouse and
您单击并保存，然后拖动并搜索并右键单击。
you click and you save and
you drag and search and right click.
VIM，你不会这么做的，都在键盘里。
VIM, you don't do any of that,
it's all in the keyboard.
所以你就换了
So you just switch.
所以现在真的很快速的是真的
And so now it's really,
really fast at VI is gonna be really,
速度真快，问题是要好好的，需要几年的时间。
really fast, the problem is to
get good at them, it takes years.
我知道有人这么做至少花了一年
I know someone that did it and
it took them at least a year and
一半的人变成了他们喜欢的水平我觉得很舒服
a half to become like to a level that
they're like, I'm comfortable with it.
但现在我看到他的时候他就在附近飞了
But now when I see him,
he's flying around.
>> Jem Young: 不是为我，我仍然使用 VS Code。
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: Not for
me, I still use VS Code.
我不是那个书呆子的人
[LAUGH] I am not that nerd level.
但是，我们今天要学习 VIM ，因为这是文本编辑器。
But, we're gonna learn VIM today
because that's the text editor.
我们会在服务器上使用编辑文件
We're gonna be use the editing
files on the server.
>> Jem Young: 为了得到这些模式，插入方式将是 i，
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: And to gets those modes,
insert mode is gonna be i,
命令方式使用 ESC ，最后一行方式仅为冒号。
command mode you use ESC, and
last line mode is just the colon.
>> Jem Young: 如何退出 VIM?
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: How to quit VIM?
这是最受欢迎的栈溢出问题之一，因为它很容易
This is one of the most popular questions
on stack overflow because it's easy
去找他们
to get into them.
你所知道的一切都不起作用，所以 Ctrl+C， Ctrl+D，
And everything you know won't work,
so Ctrl+C, Ctrl+D,
任何 ESC 的次数都不起作用
any ESC multiple times won't work.
所以如果你陷入了 ESC :q!
So, if you're ever stuck ESC :q!,
也称为惊叹号
bang with the also known
as the exclamation point.
砰的一声就是你写了什么东西，它会迫使你去救它。
The bang is just in case you wrote
something and it'll force you to save it.
它会问你是否想保存
It'll ask you if you wanna save,
你会被困住的就像退出一样
you'll get stuck the bang
just means like quit, yes.
页面就意味着，我知道我在做什么，这就是我想做的。
[LAUGH] The pages means, guess I know
what I'm doing, this is what I wanna do.
>> Jem Young: 这些是备忘单，不用担心存储它们。
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: These are cheat seats,
don't worry about memorizing them.
说实话，如果我在 VIM ，我试着做点什么，我大概也会去看看。
Honestly, if I'm in VIM and I try to do
something, I'd probably look it up too.
但你很快就能拿到基本知识了
But you'll get the basics
down pretty quickly.
就像昨天在保存档案的过程中找到东西之类的
Like yesterday, in saving a file,
finding things, things like that.
但是，可以自由地引用此页面。
But feel free to reference
back to this page.
VIM Wikia 上的复制 / 粘贴非常有用。
The copy/paste on the Wikia for
VIM is pretty useful.
但这些幻灯片在这里是一个参考。
But these slides are here is a reference.
我们不会再深入到具体的命令了
We're not gonna dive too deep into
the specific commands because again,
它是一个非常强大的文本编辑器
it's a really, really powerful text editor